Guide to the Alfred Tennyson Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Purchase from Colonel E. S. M. Prinsep, 1775-1929; Series I; 3.6; (9 boxes)
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Tennyson, Hallam
      - Incoming
        - Kettlewell, Percy W. H. ALS, Essex, 1898 Jan 3 (Box 2, Folder 155)
          Accompanied by a copy in his hand of a letter from Mary Tennyson Ker to Mrs. Matthew Allen, dated Jul 25, 1842, and draft of Hallam Tennyson's reply, dated Jan 4 1898
        - Ksasato, Takishi. ALS, Tokyo, 1904 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 156)
        - Lastow, George G. ALS, Sydney, 1903 Oct 6
        - Lauriat, Charles Emelius, Jr. TL and TLS, Boston, 1921 Aug-Sep (Box 3, Folder 157-160)
          Concerning the Edward Lear illustrations used in the Estes and Lauriat edition of Alfred Tennyson's Works (1895-1898), accompanied by: a typewritten "List of Illustrations in the Works of Alfred Lord Tennyson, published by Estes & Lauriat...1897", with pencilled annotations in the hand of Mary Emily Prinsep Hichens Tennyson; proofs of twelve etchings from Lear drawings (two copies of ten etchings) with pencilled notes in unidentified hands quoting the lines the drawings illustrate and giving the names of the etchers
        - Lear, Edward. ALS, [London], 1877 Aug 22 (Box 3, Folder 161)
          Addressed also to Lionel Tennyson. Illustrated with pen and ink sketches
        - Lefroy, Jessie. ALS, Winchester, 1925 Dec 11 (Box 3, Folder 162)
          Concerning a portrait of Jane Griffin Franklin
        - Lockyer, Tho[ma]s F. ALS, The Manse, Green Lanes, N., 1897 Oct 22 (Box 3, Folder 163)
        - Macmillan, George Augustus. ALS, London, 1925 Aug 24 (Box 3, Folder 164)
        - MaCuhlum, J. N. ALS, London, 1901 May 17 (Box 3, Folder 165)
        - Mahan, Alfred Thayer. ALS, U.S.S. Chicago, Gravesend, n.y. May 15 (Box 3, Folder 166)
        - Martineau, James. ANS, London, 1893 Mar 6 (Box 3, Folder 167)
        - Masefield, Mrs. S. 2 ALS, Staffordshire, no place, 1906, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 168)
        - Millar, H. Johnstone. TLS, Oakleigh, Marlborough, Wilts., 1925 Oct 28 (Box 3, Folder 169)
          Accompanied by three newspaper clippings concerning an anecdote about Tennyson and a draft of Hallam Tennyson's version (in Mary Emily Prinsep Hichens Tennyson's hand) of the same anecdote
        - Neilson, C. B. ALS, [London], 1884 Mar 17
        - Oakeley, Sir Herbert Stanley. ALS, [Freshwater], 1893 Jun 2 (Box 3, Folder 170)
        - Oxford University, Bodleian Library, 1895 Feb 19
          Printed form of acknowledgment, filled in and signed by E[dward] W[illiams] B[yron] Nicholson, Librarian
        - Palgrave, Francis Turner. 2 ALS, [London]; Lyme, Dorset, 1893 Jun-Sep (Box 3, Folder 171)
        - Parry, Sir Charles Hubert Hastings. ALS, [London], 1891 Nov 26 (Box 3, Folder 172)
        - Pierpont, Robert. ALS, London, 1927 Jun 26 (Box 3, Folder 173)
          Accompanied by newspaper clipping of a letter written by Robert Pierpont to The Times headed "Tennyson and Opium"
        - Ponsonby, Noel Edward. ALS, Cambridgeshire, 1925 Mar 13 (Box 3, Folder 174)
        - Ram, Balak. ALS, India, 1908 Jun 19 (Box 3, Folder 175)
        - Ratliff, J. C. ALS, Leonards on Sea, 1983 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 176)
        - Rawnsley, Willingham Franklin. 3 ALS, various places, 1914-25 (Box 3, Folder 177)
        - Rentoul, John Laurence. ALS, Liverpool, 1893 Jan 7 (Box 3, Folder 178)
        - Riviere, Briton. ALS, [London], 1897 Apr 25 (Box 3, Folder 179)
        - Rolfe, William James. 4 ALS, Cambridge, Mass., 1892, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 180)
          Concerning the Estes and Lauriat edition of Alfred Tennyson's works with the illustrations of Edward Lear. On the first page of the 1895 letter is an ANS from Hallam Tennyson to George Lillie Craik. The same letter is accompanied by a letter from Hallam Tennyson to [William James Rolfe] copied in the hand of George Lillie Craik, no date, no place
        - Rosebery, Archibald Philip Primrose ANS, [London], 1905 Dec 12 (Box 3, Folder 181)
        - Rumford, R. Kennerley. ALS, Aberdeenshire, 1914 Sep 21 (Box 3, Folder 182)
        - [Satter?], Edith Agnes. ALS, Freshwater Bay, 1894 Apr 29 (Box 3, Folder 183)
        - Scharf, Sir George. ALS, London, 1893 Sept 20 (Box 3, Folder 184)
        - Scott-Gatty, Alfred. ALS, 1883 Dec 28
          See: Box 9, folder 404
        - Sheffield, Edward Lyulph Stanley. ALS, Chesire, 1915 Jul 20 (Box 3, Folder 185)
        - Shields, Charles Woodruff. ALS, Princeton, NJ, 1897 Dec 6 (Box 3, Folder 186)
        - Shorthouse, Joseph Henry. 2 ALS, Edgbaston, Eng., 1884, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 187)
        - Signor
          See: Watts, George Frederick, Box 1, folder 201
        - Simeon, Catherine Dorothea Colville. 3 ALS, [London], 1897 Dec 10 (Box 3, Folder 188)
          Concerning Alfred Tennyson's In Memoriam
        - Simeon, Sir John Stephen Barrington, bart. ALS, [London], 1891 May 2 (Box 3, Folder 189)
          Concerning Alfred Tennyson's, In Memoriam
        - Smith, Alexander Nicholl. TLS, Springfield, Mass., 1927 Mar 18 (Box 3, Folder 190)
        - Sonnenschein, Edward Adolf. 2 ALS, Bath, 1924, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 191)
        - Spedding, James. ALS, [London], 1879 Jul 14 (Box 3, Folder 192)
          Concerning Charles Tennyson Turner's Collected Sonnets
        - Sullivan, Sir Arthur Seymour. ALS, London, 1891 Nov 24 (Box 3, Folder 193)
        - Takayasu, Michishige. ALS, Germany, 1896 Dec 6 (Box 3, Folder 194)
          Also addressed to Audrey Tennyson
        - Tennyson, Alfred. 2 ALS, 1860-[75]
          See: Box 2, folder 110
        - Tennyson, Emily Sellwood. AL, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 195)
          Incomplete: beginning and end of letter wanting
        - Tennyson, Frederick. 3 ALS, St. Ewolds, 1888-[93?] (Box 3, Folder 196)
          Concerning Alfred Tennyson's Poems by Two Brothers
        - Tennyson, Lionel. ALS, addressed also to Alfred and Emily Sellwood Tennyson, [London], 1876 Apr 29
          See: Box 1, folder 66
        - Thornycroft, Sir William Hamo. 3 ALS, [London], 1908 Feb, Jul (Box 3, Folder 197)
        - Thring, George Herbert. 2 TLS, London, 1924 Oct (Box 3, Folder 198)
        - Van Dyke, Henry. ALS, [New York], 1897 Dec 6 (Box 3, Folder 199)
        - Ward, Louisa Edith Simeon. ALS, [London], [1891] May 3 (Box 3, Folder 200)
        - Watts, George Frederick. ALS, Guildford, 1901 Aug 14 (Box 3, Folder 201)
          Signed "Signor"
        - Watts, Mary Fraser Tytler. 5 ALS, [1899?]-1908 (Box 3, Folder 202)
        - Way, Sir Samuel James, bart. TLS, North Adelaide, 1913 Jul 14 (Box 3, Folder 203)
        - Wellington, Arthur Charles Wellesley, fourth duke of. ALS, [London], 1911 May 17 (Box 3, Folder 204)
        - Williamson, Francis John. ALS, Surrey, 1893 Aug 23 (Box 3, Folder 205)
        - Woods, Albert William. ALS, London, 1883 Dec 20 (Box 3, Folder 206)
        - Woods, James J. AL in an unidentified hand, signed by Woods, Grand Worthy Secretary of the Independent Order of Good Templars, Birmingham, 1882 Apr 1 (Box 3, Folder 207)
        - Woolner, Alice Gertrude (Waugh). ALS, London, 1901 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 208)
          Accompanied by a pencilled note in Mary Tennyson's hand, dated 1901
        - Wordsworth, Gordon. ALS, Ambleside, 1919 Mar 7 (Box 3, Folder 209)
        - Wright, Arthur. ALS, Lincoln, 1894 Aug 20 (Box 3, Folder 210)
        - Wright, William Aldis. 3 ALS, Cambridge, 1907, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 211)
        - Unidentified. ALS, Datchet House, Datchet, 1917 Oct 28 (Box 3, Folder 212)
        - Empty envelope, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 213)
      - Outgoing
        - ALS (draft) to Henry Montagu Butler, concerning the manuscript of In Memoriam, Isle of Wight, 1897 Dec 10 (Box 3, Folder 214)
          On the fourth page is a copy (in Hallam Tennyson's hand) of a letter from Catherine Simeon to Henry Montagu Butler, dated Dec 9, 1897
        - 2 ALS to Andrew [Hichens], [1892], 1899 (Box 3, Folder 215)
        - Letter (incomplete and in an unidentified hand) to [Sir James Thomas] Knowles, Farringford, 1896 Dec 20 (Box 3, Folder 216)
        - AL (draft) to [Julia] Lennard, Farringford, 1884 Feb 20 (Box 3, Folder 217)
          Sister of Arthur Hallam
        - ALS to "May", Surrey, 1887 Jul 18 (Box 3, Folder 218)
          Mary Emily Prinsep, wife of Andrew Hichens and later of Hallam Tennyson
        - ALS to [Hardwicke Drummond] Rawnsley, Isle of Wight, 1896 Mar 30 (Box 3, Folder 219)
          Concerning William Wordsworth
        - ALS (draft) to "Jack" [Sir John Stephen Barrington Simeon?], Isle of Wight, 1891 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 220)
          Concerns Alfred Tennyson's In Memoriam
        - 30 letters to his mother, Emily Sellwood Tennyson, 1869-92 (Box 3, Folder 221-223)
        - ALS to Lionel Tennyson, Isle of Wight, [185-?] (Box 3, Folder 224)
        - 3 ALS to Charles Tennyson [Turner], [1826-33] (Box 3, Folder 225)
          Letter of [1826 or 1827?] is incomplete
    - Tennyson, Emily Sellwood
      - Incoming
        - British Museum. Printed form of acknowledgement, with name and date added in an unidentified hand and signed by A[nthony] Panizzi, 1860 Dec 12 (Box 4, Folder 226)
        - Browning, Elizabeth Barrett. 2 ANS, London, 1852 Jul-Sep (Box 4, Folder 227)
        - Carlyle, Jane Baillie Welsh. 2 ALS, London and Dover, 1856, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 228)
        - Cator, Julia Maria Frances Hallam
          See: Lennard, Julia Maria Frances Hallam, Box 4, folder 234
        - Chapman, B. L. 2 ALS, London, [1855, 1862] (Box 4, Folder 229)
          1855 letter mutilated
        - Chlapowska, Helena Modjeska
          See: Modjeska, Helena, Box 4, folder 237
        - Clough, Arthur Hugh. ALS, [Spain], [1861] Aug 13 (Box 4, Folder 230)
        - Forster, John. ALS, [London], 1857 May 9 (Box 4, Folder 231)
        - Franklin, Jane Griffin. 3 ALS, various places, 1856-73 (Box 4, Folder 232)
          Concerns Elisha Kent Kane; Emma, Queen Consort of Kaméhaméhe IV, King of Hawaii; Alfred Tennyson's "To the Queen"
        - Franklin, Jane Griffin. ALS to Alfred Tennyson, [1873 Mar 22]
          Addressed also to Emily Sellwood Tennyson; it is preceded by a note written in an unidentified hand
          See: Box 1, folder 17
        - Hallam, Julia Maria Frances
        - Hughes, Margaret Watts, ALS, London, 1887 Apr 29
        - Lear, Edward. 3 ALS, various places, 1851-79 (Box 4, Folder 233)
          Accompanied by scraps of three other letters. Letter of 1879 Apr 4 illustrated with two pen and ink sketches
        - Lennard, Julia Maria Frances Hallam. ALS, Surrey, England, [1872?] Sep 30 (Box 4, Folder 234)
        - Locker-Lampson, Frederick. ALS, Lucerne, 1869 Jul 2 (Box 4, Folder 235)
          Signed also by Alfred Tennyson
        - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth. ALS, Bonchurch, 1868 Jul 19 (Box 4, Folder 236)
        - Modjeska, Helena. ANS to [Emily Sellwood Tennyson?] (Box 4, Folder 237)
        - Owen, Sir Richard. 2 ALS, [London], 1866, n.y. (Box 4, Folder 238)
          The top half of the undated letter is wanting
        - Panizzi, Sir Anthony
          See: British Museum, Box 4, folder 226
        - Paul, Mr. ALS, Bailie, Wimborne, 1864 Oct 14 (Box 4, Folder 239)
          Incomplete; latter part of letter missing
        - Shorthouse, Joseph Henry. ALS, Lansdowne, Edgbaston, England, 1888 Apr 3 (Box 4, Folder 240)
        - Simeon, Sir John, bart., ALS, Swanston, Isle of Wight, 1859 Aug 29 (Box 4, Folder 241)
          Concerns George Frederick Watts
        - Taylor, Theodosia Alicia Ellen Frances Charlotte Spring-Rice. ALS, Bournemouth, [1864] Aug 2 (Box 4, Folder 242)
        - Tennyson, Alfred. 6 AL and 6 ALS, [ca. 1850-77]
          See: Box 2, folder 109
        - Tennyson, Frederick. AL and 3 ALS, various places, [185-?]-60 (Box 4, Folder 243)
          Both 1854 letters also addressed to Alfred Tennyson; beginning and end of [185-] letter wanting
        - Tennyson, Hallam. 30 ALS, 1869-92
        - Tennyson, Lionel. ALS, addressed also to Alfred and Hallam Tennyson, [London], 1876 Apr 29
        - Thackeray, William Makepeace. ALS, Kensington, [1852 Feb 4] (Box 4, Folder 244)
        - Ward, Louisa Edith (Simeon). ALS, [London], 1869 Mar 20 (Box 4, Folder 245)
          Parts of pages 3 and 4 missing Removed from: Catalogue of pictures...at Farringford (box 9, folder 403)
        - Watts, George Frederick. 3 ALS, London, 1859-65 (Box 4, Folder 246)
        - Unidentified correspondent. ALS (fragment), 1849 Mar 26 (Box 4, Folder 247)
        - Empty envelopes, 1842-77 (Box 4, Folder 248-253)
      - Outgoing
        - ALS (draft) to Charles Lutwidge Dodgson, Isle of Wight, [1870 March] (Box 4, Folder 254)
        - ALS to [Mary Emily Prinsep], Farringford, 1874 Oct 5 (Box 4, Folder 255)
        - ALS to Henry Sellwood, [Farringford], [1860? May] (Box 4, Folder 256)
          Appended to a copy of a letter written by Prince Albert to Alfred Tennyson, May 17, 1860. Concerning Alfred Tennyson's Idylls of the King
        - Tennyson, Alfred. 2 AL (fragments), 1876, n.d.
          See: Box 1, folder 64
        - Tennyson, Hallam. AL, n.d.
          See: Box 3, folder 195
    - Other Tennyson Family
      - Brassey, Thomas Brassey, 1st earl of. New Year's greeting for 1906 in the form of a printed leaflet "An Old Man in Retrospect" by Benjamin Jowett, with autograph inscription to "Mrs. Andrew" [Mary Emily Prinsep Hichens, later Lady Tennyson], signed "B" (Box 4, Folder 257)
      - Hallam, Arthur Henry, ALS to Septimus Tennyson, [London], [1832?] Apr 3 (Box 4, Folder 258)
      - Hallam, Julia Maria Frances
      - Japikse, Cornelia Geertrui Hendrika. 2 ALS to Mary Emily Prinsep Hichens Tennyson, [no place and The Hague], [1924?, 1926] (Box 4, Folder 259)
      - Jenner, Charles. 2 ALS to Mary Emily Prinsep Hichens Tennyson, Midlothian, 1893 Sep (Box 4, Folder 260)
      - Jesse, Emily Tennyson. 4 ALS to Alfred Tennyson, [185?-75?]
        See: Box 1, folder 29
      - Jesse, Emily Tennyson. Signature clipped from a letter, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 261)
      - Macmillan, George Augustus. ALS to Mary Emily Prinsep Hichens Tennyson, London, 1924 Dec 22 (Box 4, Folder 262)
      - Scholfield, Alwyn Faber. ALS and TLS to Mary Emily Prinsep Hichens Tennyson, Cambridge, 1929 Jan (Box 4, Folder 263)
      - Takayasu, Michishige to Hallam Tennyson. ALS, Germany, 1896 Dec 6
        Also addressed to Audrey Tennyson.
        See: Box 3, folder 194
      - Tennyson, Audrey Georgiana Florence Boyle. ALS to "May", [Farringford], [1892 Oct 11] (Box 4, Folder 264)
        "May" is Mary Emily Prinsep Hichens, later Lady Tennyson
      - [Tennyson, Elizabeth Fytche]. AL in verse to [Hallam and Lionel Tennyson], [Rosemount, Hampstead?], [ca. 1859] (Box 4, Folder 265)
        Paper watermarked 1859
      - Tennyson, Elizabeth Fytche. ALS to Alfred Tennyson, [Hampstead], 1860 Jan 10
        See: Box 1, folder 63
      - Tennyson, Emily Sellwood. ALS to [Mary Emily Prinsep], Farringford, 1874 Oct 5
        See: Box 4, folder 255
      - Tennyson, Frederick. ALS to Alfred Tennyson, St. Ewolds, 1884 Jan 23
        See: Box 1, folder 65
      - Tennyson, Frederick. 3 ALS to Hallam Tennyson, St. Ewolds, 1888-[93?]
        Concerning Alfred Tennyson's Poems by Two Brothers.
        See: Box 3, folder 196
      - Tennyson, George. ALS to [Elizabeth Tennyson] Russell, 1828 [Jan 1] (Box 4, Folder 266)
      - Tennyson, George Clayton. ALS to [Elizabeth Tennyson] Russell, Somersby, 1822 Jun 18 (Box 4, Folder 267)
      - Tennyson, Hallam. ALS to Emily Sellwood Sellwood, Alfred, and Lionel Tennyson, 1869 Apr 4
        See: Box 3, folder 221
      - Tennyson, Hallam. ALS to Lionel Tennyson, Isle of Wight, [185-?]
        See: Box 3, folder 224
      - Tennyson, Hallam. ALS to "May", Surrey, 1887 Jul 18
        Mary Emily Prinsep, wife of Andrew Hichens and later of Hallam Tennyson.
        See: Box 3, folder 218
      - Tennyson, Lionel. ALS to Mrs. Field, Farringford, n.y. Jun 12 (Box 4, Folder 268)
        The letter refers to Alfred Tennyson
      - Tennyson, Hallam. 3 ALS to Charles Tennyson [Turner], [1826-33]
        See: Box 3, folder 225
      - [Turner, Charles Tennyson?] ALS fragment to unidentified recipient, Grasby, 1860 Aug 23 (Box 4, Folder 269)
      - [Turner, Charles Tennyson?] ALS fragment to unidentified recipient, Grasby Vicarage, 1864 Jun 4 (Box 4, Folder 270)
      - Turner, Rev. Samuel. ALS to [Mr. Turner], Cambridge, 1775 Nov 6 (Box 4, Folder 271)
      - Waite, John. 2 ALS to Charles Tennyson Turner, Manby Rectory, England, 1864-65 (Box 4, Folder 272)
        The letter of December 23, 1864 is written on the back of a circular appealing for funds on behalf of the Louth Grammar School
      - Walker, Catherine Taylor, ALS to Mary Emily Prinsep Hichens Tennyson, [1928] Dec 5 (Box 4, Folder 273)
      - Warren, Sir Thomas Herbert. ALS to Mary Emily Prinsep Hichens Tennyson, Oxford, 1921 Sep 28 (Box 4, Folder 274)
    - Other Correspondence
      - "To the author of Miss Hitchcock's Wedding Gown." ALS, draft, signed "A Lover of Truth", 1879 Mar (Box 4, Folder 275)
      - Brassey, Thomas. 2 ALS to Andrew Hichens, Normanhurst Court, Battle., 1889 May 16-18 (Box 4, Folder 276)
        The letter of May 18 is incomplete
      - Buchheim, C. A. TLS (carbon) to the Editor of the Times, 1892 Oct 17 (Box 4, Folder 277)
        Titled "Tennyson in Germany"
      - Buckland, Francis Trevelyan. ALS to George Douglas, London, [1865?] Mar 4 (Box 4, Folder 278)
      - Harrison, Frederic. 3 ALS to Andrew Hichens concerning Alfred Tennyson, 1890 Sep-Nov (Box 4, Folder 279)
        Accompanied by a note by Hallam Tennyson
      - Heath, Douglas Devon. AL to Mr. Booker, Kitlands, 1892 Oct 19 (Box 4, Folder 280)
        Incomplete: pages seven through ten remain, plus part of pages one and two
      - Lytton, Edward Robert Bulwer-Lytton. AL (copy in an unidentified hand) to Mary Anderson [de Navarro], Paris, 1888 Apr 26 (Box 4, Folder 281)
      - Macmillan & Co., firm, London. Copy of a letter to Messrs. Goupil and Company, London, 1889 Jan 23 (Box 4, Folder 282)
        Conveying Alfred Tennyson's agreement to their terms for the reproduction of 25 of Edward Lear's illustrations for 3 of Tennyson's poems
      - Paul, Margaret A. ALS to Mrs. Taylor [Theodosia Alicia Monteagle Taylor], Bailie, [1864] Sep 13 (Box 4, Folder 283)
      - R., A. I. to E. M. R. ALS, copy in an unidentified hand (Box 4, Folder 284)
      - Simeon, Catherine Dorothea Colville. AN (in Hallam Tennyson's hand) to Henry Montagu Butler, signed by Simeon, 1897 Dec 10 (Box 4, Folder 285)
      - S[trahan], A[lexander]. ALS to William Ishister, Edinburgh, 1870 Dec 28 (Box 4, Folder 286)
      - Weiss, Ch[arles?]. ALS to [Julia Margaret] Pattle Cameron, Berlin, 1869 Sep 24 (Box 4, Folder 287)
      - Whewell, William. AL (copy in an unidentified hand) to Thomas Spring-Rice Monteagle, Cambridge, 1859 Oct 21 (Box 4, Folder 288)
      - Unidentified to Mrs. Rawnsley, [1844] Jan 1 (Box 4, Folder 289)
      - Unidentified fragments of correspondence, 1844-64, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 290)
  - WRITINGS
    - Tennyson, Alfred
      - "Alexander," autograph manuscript sonnet. London, [1872?] (Box 4, Folder 291)
      - "Carmen Sæculare: An ode in honor of the Jubilee of Queen Victoria," page proof with manuscript corrections in the poet's hand and also in the hand of Hallam Tennyson (Box 4, Folder 292)
      - "The Charge of the Light Brigade," printed leaf with manuscript corrections in the poet's hand and also in the hand of Emily Sellwood Tennyson, 1855? (Box 4, Folder 293)
        The third version
      - "The Charge of the Heavy Brigade at Balaclava," page proof with manuscript corrections in the hand of Hallam Tennyson, [1882?] (Box 4, Folder 294)
      - "The City Child," autograph manuscript poem of two stanzas, five lines each, [1880?] (Box 4, Folder 295)
      - "The Cup, A Tragedy", autograph manuscript of 7 lines from Act II (beginning: "Nay, rather then so clip"), [1884?] (Box 4, Folder 296)
      - "The Death of the Duke of Clarence and Avondale," page proof of the printing in The Nineteenth Century with autograph manuscript corrections, [1892?] (Box 5, Folder 297)
      - "Despair," autograph manuscript of the prose argument to the poem, [1885?] (Box 5, Folder 298)
      - "Did the Young Lord Espy Us," first line of an unfinished poem of six lines, written in his hand (Box 5, Folder 299)
      - "Dora," autograph manuscript, [1842?-78?] (Box 5, Folder 300)
        First published in Poems, London, 1842, these lines (with the exception of one phrase) correspond to the revised version printed in the Works, London, 1878
      - "The Foresters," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 301)
        Two choruses of the Forester's song and 67 lines from Act II, Scene I; and 44 lines from Act IV, Scene I, (including cancellations and alternative readings)
      - "God bless our Prince and Bride", autograph manuscript of 2 stanzas added to "God Save the Queen", [1858?] (Box 5, Folder 302)
        On the occasion of the Princess Royal's wedding, slightly different from the published version
      - "Helen's Tower," typescript, [1885?] (Box 5, Folder 303)
        With a copy of Tennyson's accomanying note and Emily Sellwood Tennyson's postscript to Lord Dufferin
      - Idylls of the King
        - Dedication to "Idylls of the King", page proof of the [1862? edition] with autograph manuscript corrections (Box 5, Folder 304)
        - Dedication to Idylls of the King, manuscript copy of an early version [?] in an unidentified hand, [1862?] (Box 5, Folder 305)
          Differs in many respects from the published version
        - "Geraint and Enid," autograph manuscript of six lines beginning "My charger and her palfrey" (Box 5, Folder 306)
          Written on a scrap of paper torn from a folded sheet with autograph manuscript of 3 lines beginning "But fear not: I will die a dozen deaths"
        - "Guinevere," autograph manuscript of 4 stanzas of the novice's song, beginning "Late, late, so late", [1859?] (Box 5, Folder 307)
        - "The Marriage of Geraint," autograph manuscript of two lines from Enid's song, beginning "Turn turn thy wheel, False Fortune smile or frown", [1857?] (Box 5, Folder 308)
        - "Merlin and Vivien," autograph manuscript of 3 lines beginning "But fear not: I will die a dozen deaths" (in two versions)
          With lines from "Geraint and Enid" written on a scrap of paper torn from a folded sheet
          See: "Geraint and Enid", Box 5, folder 306
        - "Merlin and Vivien," page proof of 302 lines (beginning "Says she not well?") with autograph manuscript corrections, [1859?] (Box 5, Folder 309)
        - "Nimue"
          See: "Merlin and Vivien", Box 5, folder 308
      - "Jack Tar," autograph manuscript of four 7-line stanzas (3 lines of a fifth stanza have been crossed out), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 310)
        A few words of stanza four have been cut away
      - "Jubilee Ode"
        See: "Carmen Sæculare", Box 4, folder 292
      - "The Lover's Tale," page proofs, [1833, 1879] (Box 5, Folder 311)
        Page proofs of a portion of the 1833 privately printed edition beginning "Fainted at intervals and grew again") with autograph manuscript corrections Accompanied by page proofs of a portion of the 1879 edition, beginning "The path was perilous" and beginning "Of life issueth") with autograph manuscript corrections
      - "Lucretius," manuscript poem, 1868 Jan 28 (Box 5, Folder 312)
        Possibly in the hand of Emily Sellwood Tennyson
      - "The Miller's Daughter," autograph manuscript poem, [1842?] (Box 5, Folder 313)
        Stanzas 1-9 and 19-21 and the first six lines of the first song are wanting
      - "Minnie and Winnie," autograph manuscript poem of 5 stanzas, four lines each, [1880?] (Box 5, Folder 314)
        Autograph manuscript poem of 5 stanzas, four lines each